<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The tree of humane life, or, The bloud of the grape Proving the possibilitie of maintaining humane life from infancy to extreme old age without any sicknesse by the use of wine. By Tobias Whitaker Doctor in Physick of London.</title>
            <author>Whitaker, Tobias, d. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15052</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25356</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119853</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855059</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855059</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20529</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15052)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20529)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1047:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The tree of humane life, or, The bloud of the grape Proving the possibilitie of maintaining humane life from infancy to extreme old age without any sicknesse by the use of wine. By Tobias Whitaker Doctor in Physick of London.</title>
                  <author>Whitaker, Tobias, d. 1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 73, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I[ohn] D[awson] for H[enry] O[verton] and are to be sold at his shop in Popes-head Ally,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's and bookseller's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>F6 bears text in Latin signed: Alexander Reidus.</note>
                  <note>With a final imprimatur leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wine --  Therapeutic use --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Wine and wine making --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20529:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20529:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TREE OF HVMANE LIFE, <hi>OR,</hi> THE BLOVD OF THE GRAPE.</p>
            <p>PROVING THE POS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilitie of maintaining hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane life from infancy to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame old age without any ſickneſſe by the uſe of Wine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> TOBIAS WHITAKER <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor in Phyſick of</hi> London.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I.D.</hi> for <hi>H.O.</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Popes-head Ally. 1638.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20529:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20529:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentle Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I would have made any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I could ſtoope no lower then a Prince: the ſubject me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riteth aſmuch, had it beene handled accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly: and if it had, yet I durſt not flye ſo high,
<pb facs="tcp:20529:3"/>though <hi>Riolanus</hi> taketh boldneſſe to tell <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth of France, that the faculty deſerveth the patronage of a Prince, both in reſpect of anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, neceſsity, ſubject, and office; For Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie a twinne with the Divine, for ſo ſoone as the ſoule was breathed into man, it was then <hi>Corpus humanum vivens &amp; ſanabile,</hi> and ſo the ſubject both of Phiſicke
<pb facs="tcp:20529:3"/>and Theologie: for had <hi>Adam</hi> never ſinned, yet muſt his body have been preſerved and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by diet, which is part of phyſick. But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his fall ſo violated his equall temper, that as then hee became ſubject to mortalitie and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall decay. Then came in the neceſsity of medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, and ever ſince for this neceſsitie ſake, hath the Almighty comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:20529:4"/>an honour to bee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Phiſician, for he hath created him an Angell of mercy. Alſo in reſpect of the ſubject about which this art is exerciſed, it rightly challengeth precedence of all other faculties (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept Theologie) for it is the body of man: a world, a wonder, the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God himſelfe, and ſuch a piece of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitecture, as the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie
<pb facs="tcp:20529:4"/>would not vouchſafe to frame with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Councell. The of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice then of preſerving and maintaining it, muſt needs bee high and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, and may well befit a King to exerciſe: Such eſteeme it had obtained when <hi>Avicenna, Iſaac,</hi> and other Princes were Phiſicians: nay, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty hath crowned ſome to this day with ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of Prince, witneſſe the
<pb facs="tcp:20529:5"/>houſe <hi>de Medicis.</hi> And if I ſhould ſay it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends all other fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties I dare attempt the proving of it. Firſt in reſpect of government as Agents they ought to be obeyed in practice, even by Princes, for they are ſubject to ſickneſſe and muſt die like men; and Iudges which have po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to condemne poore malefactors or others, yet they muſt receive their
<pb facs="tcp:20529:5"/>ſentence of death from the Phiſician, if they come to a faire and time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly end. And as they make lawes for the well orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and governing the Republique. So doth the Phyſician preſcribe rules, for the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of harmony through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this little world, but <hi>ab quantum mutatus ab il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo!</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, was his Motto in <hi>Homer.</hi> Now if <hi>Stercus</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20529:6"/>can bee pickt out of the vanities of <hi>Cornelius Agrippa,</hi> it ſhal be thrown upon the purple robes of the Phyſician, by the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant or impudent. For Science hath no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy but ignorance, nor is vilified among any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept pigritious and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent perſons. Then let the ignorant prattle, ſtill the Phyſitian ſhall be the inſtrument of all common good in a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publique,
<pb facs="tcp:20529:6"/>and if no vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinarie man of any condition bee able to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect any ſolid good, either to his King, Countrie, or ſelfe, as he is not, and the power of reſtoring and healing him, bee given principally to the Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian. And if alſo upon that prolongation of life, if upon but one houre or moment eternity doth or may depend, then conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the Phyſician
<pb facs="tcp:20529:7"/>muſt bee acknowledged an inſtrument of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, principally to the body, accidentally to the ſoule. What if I ſhall ſeeme in the eyes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to advance my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, higher then their judgements wil imbrace? yet can I not juſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a frowne, where a probable truth is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt: nor is my intention, hereby to undervalue any perſon or judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb facs="tcp:20529:7"/>nor overvalue my owne, whatſoever <hi>Cicero</hi> ſhall affirme to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary in theſe words <hi>Nemingem unquam, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Poetam, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Oratorem fuiſſe, qui quenquam me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liorem, quàm ſe arbitrare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> but rather to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate my faculty of thoſe contempts and diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements, which vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſpoſitions caſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. What I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten concerning the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent
<pb facs="tcp:20529:8"/>ſubject, begs nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther acceptation, nor en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comiaſtick favour, nor doe I quit my ſelfe of temerity; <hi>Suffenus</hi> will be a companion for the beſt learned, and ſome wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe will eſcape the tongue and pen of the wiſeſt man, in this or that thing. Therefore I doe feare no frowne (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept from my naturall Prince) and thoſe whom he hath commanded me
<pb facs="tcp:20529:8"/>to feare and obey, and thus as a loyall ſubject I doe. In teſtimony wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I have indeavoured to open this myſterie of life and health to my King and Countrey. If I have fruſtrated any expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the handling of it, let my <hi>velle</hi> be accepted, <hi>in magnis eſt voluiſſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20529:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20529:9"/>
            <head>THE TREE OF LIFE; OR, THE BLOVD OF THE GRAPE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His ſubject is bloud, in that is life; 'tis of the Vine, and that the plant of life; And if I ſhould ſay a Species of that in Paradiſe; my opinion might not in all places, and amongſt all perſons bee rejected: <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis</hi> and <hi>minùs,</hi> may be the difference; for as that was called the Tree of life, ſo is the Vine, and they doe not only agree in the appellation, but in their
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20529:10"/>nature and effects alſo. In teſtimonie hereof <hi>Aſelepiades</hi> the Phiſitian, both to my former diſtinction, as alſo to the appellation affirmeth, The nature of Wine to be neereſt to the nature of the <hi>Gods,</hi> and their nature is incorrupt. Secondly, he adviſeth the applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it to unſound bodies to reduce them to a ſound and incorrupt tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and in ſome ſence to eternitie, for ſuch a ſtate there is in this world as will be more plainly demonſtrated in our following diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>How neceſſary then is this ſubject, and how difficult to explicate? Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary becauſe life is ſhort, difficult be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe art is long: yet if by this Act I ſhall bee an inſtrument, to protract life and abreviate art, not only ſhew the plant, but teach the uſe, it may prove worth my labour and Countries ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation.</p>
            <p>How ever reaſon and Philoſophie ſhall be my guide, neither <hi>Hippocrates</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:20529:10"/>nor <hi>Galen</hi> nor any other authority, further then they are my owne, and agree with reaſon and truth. As for the abbreviation of art, preſervation of life, and reſtauration of health; wee will comprehend in a ſmall circle, and render in a few words, the ſumme of all Claſſick Writers, to this purpoſe, eſpecially the Foureteene bookes of <hi>Galen</hi> his method of curing, and Six of health preſerving: and in theſe few words expreſt <hi>(viz.)</hi> Dyet and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine: for thus chiefly and ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and by theſe two wayes are life and health extended and reſtored, quantity, quality, and manner of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication in them obſerved. Quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as it is <hi>vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad vaſa &amp; ad vires;</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, as it correſponds with humane bodies in generall, or with this and that individuall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Leſsius</hi> ſeemeth to mee to dote more upon quantity <hi>ad vaſa,</hi> then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other thing conducing to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20529:11"/>of life, and yet ſuch a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity as is not <hi>ad vaſa,</hi> as if Satiation were the Uſher of diſeaſes, corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and mortality: which I ſuppoſe differeth very much from the ſence of <hi>Galen,</hi> (that is) to preſcribe a <hi>pondus</hi> or ſtreight weight and meaſure of nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment to all tempers, and ſuch a weight not to be exceeded upon any occaſion. But if hee be underſtood to ſpeake only to men in religious Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and ſuch as impoveriſh their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to elevate their mindes to pious thoughts and exerciſes, then his Twelve ounces will bee better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood and little blamed: but in a phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſence cannot ſtand with the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of art. For <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> both, will tell him diſeaſes are cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by contrarieties. Inanition by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, muſt bee cured by repletion in feeding; and this inanition may bee extreame or not extreame, and then no conſtant <hi>Pondus</hi> ought to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20529:11"/>But if I underſtand thoſe Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies, then thus I explicate their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in this point, and ſo will leave the Iefuite to his owne order. As for the quality of aliment, that it be <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogeneall,</hi> pleaſant and familiar to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane conſtitutions and tempers, not only in generall, but alſo to every in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividuall, is a point that the Ancients were ſtrict obſervers of, and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out much diſcretion. For the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Phiſitian is moſt ſeene in his election of aliment in quality an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering the temper of the body. For though a diſeaſe muſt be cured by his contrary, yet the temper of the body muſt be preſerved by its own Simile; as heate by heate, and moiſture by moiſture: but the degree whether more or leſſe intenſe is judicated by nature, and to be ordered by the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian; But this is a paradox to vulgar practicers, who argue falſely upon a true ground, for when <hi>Hippocrates</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:20529:12"/>ſaith, <hi>Contraria contrarijs curantur;</hi> they like an ignorant Iury will runne altogether upon contraries, both in curing, and alſo in nouriſhing, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my Simile, making no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene honeſty and diſhone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, or contrary and contrary. 'Tis true, contrary remedies muſt be, and are moſt rationally adminiſtred in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the body, becauſe a crooked ſticke muſt bee bent as farre the other way to make it ſtreight, according to <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi> But if contraries ſhall bee adhibited to a harmonious temper 'tis the cauſe of diſcord and conflict in Nature. As for example: In a hot and moiſt temper to uſe a cold and dry dyet; Therefore it appeareth plainly that the quality of aliment ought to bee moſt obſerved; But for Quantity that is left to the free choice of Nature, becauſe naturall choice is never <hi>ultra capacitatem recipientis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to ſpeake more fully to <hi>Leſsius,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:20529:12"/>who in a religious way diſputeth prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally for temperance; yet ſo ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that I muſt tell him, as a Phiſitian, the Fathers of our Art preferre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe (ſo it be not in the higheſt degree of exceſſe) before ſuch temperance, and of two evils the leaſt: For they lay it downe Canonically that all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of plenitude or fulneſſe, are ſafer for the body then diſeaſes of empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: And I apprehend much reaſon, and variety of reaſons in this axiome.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe univerſall evacuation is ſooner effected then repletion; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, becauſe accidents of various formes cannot be avoided, for they are infinite, and the leaſt affliction falling upon an extenuate or leſſiate body, for want of a ſufficiencie of excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentitious humours to move in, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not only a dangerous aſſault to the radicall ſpirits, but without ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den reſiſtance of art, muſt tyranniſe nature before enfeebled and kept un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20529:13"/>cannot of it ſelfe reſiſt to expell it. Which meere reſiſtance of nature or labour to expell noxious humours doth beget a Feaver, and that only <hi>ex conatu natura</hi> (according to <hi>Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorus à vega</hi>) naturall heate is fired and not otherwiſe, by the aſcent of putrid fuliginous vapours to the heart, or if medicine be adhibited, yet ſuch a body muſt ſuffer from both and life be ſhortned.</p>
            <p>Contrarily, where there is a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent quantity of excrementitious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours for diſeaſes to involve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in, there are they reteyned with leſſe danger or oppreſſion to the radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſpirits: and removed by medicine with as little offence, as I ſhall demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate more Philoſophically in this manner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alberius</hi> (amongſt other Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers) doth conſtitute a twofold moiſture in mixt bodies; One which he calleth <hi>Humidum continuans,</hi> and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20529:13"/>from this continuating humidity pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth an unction of parts for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they would bee altogether dry and conſequently diſunited: But there is no naturall body void of this hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midity, though never ſo hard or dry, but hath a ſufficient moiſture to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyne their parts together <hi>inter ſe:</hi> and every Alchymiſt proveth this truth by practice, and daily extracting oyle out of the hardeſt and dryeſt bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. Therefore this humidity is right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nominated by ſome Phiſitians <hi>Olea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginoſum Humidum,</hi> oylie humidity conſiſting of ayrie and aqueous moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture.</p>
            <p>The other humidity is <hi>Humidum quaſi nutriens,</hi> as it were the nouriſhing moiſture, and this is a watriſh humidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the mixt body, nothing advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious to the continuation of parts, and is eaſily reſolved becauſe of its tenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo is not the oleaginous, becauſe of its craſſitude: So that where a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20529:14"/>of excrementitious humours, by reaſon of a ſevere dyet is wanting in the body of man, both diſeaſe and medicine muſt needs bee more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full over the fixed moiſture and heate, which is the ligament of life.</p>
            <p>Contrarily where there is a ſecond moiſture to entertaine, either effect or medicine doth leſſe harme. But I intend no controverſie with <hi>Leſſius,</hi> therefore I will returne to my proper ſubject, and ſhew how every temper may be preſerved void of all diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, or ſuch as ariſe out of the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall principles of nature by the true uſe of wine, and alſo pove it to be an excellent remedy, applyed according to proper judication, and may prove ſpecificall in diſeaſes of every nature, ariſing out of the aforeſaid principles, paſſing as dilucidly and briefly as may bee through all the parts of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Curioſitie</hi> hath newly conceived,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20529:14"/>and will now ſuffer abortion, if a taſte of this promiſed juyce be not ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſented whoſe nature and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency is encomiaſtick, ſufficient, ſo tranſcending all other nutriment, as that juſt <hi>Noah</hi> makes it the firſt act of his husbandry: and planted a Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard before either corne or any other graine, as is affirmed by ſacred teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. The reaſon if I ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to offer, <hi>Ne Sutor ultra crepidam,</hi> I muſt expect from divines, and juſtly, if I ſhould adventure to explicate any text of holy writ, without qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yet will I not ſo inthrall my fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, or ſuffocate ſuch motions as may bee advantagious to a rationall man, without prying into the Arke; as not only to take notice of this plantation to be the firſt act of husbandry, but eſpecially of his age, which was Nine hundred and fifty. His age extended Twenty yeares beyond <hi>Adam,</hi> in whom the principles of Nature were
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20529:15"/>moſt firme and pure; And no reaſon can argue otherwiſe, but that in courſe of Nature, being ſo many Centuries after <hi>Adam,</hi> the yeares of <hi>Noah</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily muſt have bin ſhorter by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſcore then were his Grandſires yeares, had he not taſted <hi>Nectar</hi> from that plant from which <hi>Adam</hi> was excluded, I meane an inferiour ſpecies of that tree of life: For had it beene equall in power, whereas he lived af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his plantation Three hundred and fifty yeares (a good cordiall to an old man) hee had beene now alive, and ſo ſhould have beene for ever. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, in Six hundred yeares hee could not but conclude, and determine moſt naturall queſtions by experience, and thereby ſufficiently taught out of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſals how to draw his particular concluſions, or otherwiſe by reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them into their naturall princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, make a ſenſible diſcovery of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſecrets. And out of this fulneſſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20529:15"/>of knowledge and experience, doth he plant his Vineyard; So that by infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence the excellency of this ſubject doth appeare tranſcendent; Now let us really conſider the nature and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of it, with its difference and uſe, both in reſpect of aliment and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cament and application to every indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viduall, of what age or temper ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
            <p>And to the end we may act aſmuch as wee ſpeake, Let us looke upon the quality of Wine philoſophically, and at the firſt view wee ſhall diſcover a two-fold heate in it, as it flowes from a living body <hi>(viz.)</hi> an animall and elementary heate, for though wine cannot be ſaid to be <hi>animatum,</hi> ſuch as giveth a ſoule or life, yet it may carry with it and to it ſelfe, an impreſſe cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tral orimplanted heate from a ſoule, as may bee demonſtrated plainly in other things: for the ſeed of animals aſwell as of plants, have not a ſoule
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20529:16"/>in act, according to the doctrine of <hi>Ariſtotle:</hi> Yet it doth take from a ſoule ſuch a generative power like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſoule, which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith is nothing elſe but a vitall heate, which hee hath diſtinguiſhed from igneous and elementary. So as in the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a living creature the firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving is animal, or the plant from which the ſeed iſſueth, but the ſeed is the inſtrument, which by a power received from the plant (that is to ſay) by a vitall heate; begetteth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being like it ſelfe. Since there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is <hi>in ſemine,</hi> a vitall heate, diſtinct from elementary, why may we not ſay the ſame of wine, which in like manner iſſueth from an animate body? Then wine hath a double heat, or one conflate or moved out of two: and that which is great and intenſe doth not conſiſt of an indiviſible, but in ſome certaine latitude, and it is now greater or leſſe according to the varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20529:16"/>of Species, as alſo from the diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of places; for in more hot places where the Sunne effects a ſtronger heate, there grow hotter Wines, and this heate in them is not externall, but rather naturall and implanted in the wine: For from the heate of the place it commeth to paſſe that the vitall and elementary heate, which conſtituteth the naturall heate of the wine, doth become greater and more intenſe: So as wee cannot deny in wine that dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble moiſture: and <hi>Galen</hi> is of the ſame opinion, when as hee diſtinguiſheth the ſubſtance <hi>vinoſa</hi> from the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance <hi>aquoſa,</hi> for <hi>vinoſa qualitas,</hi> hath that humidity which doth unite the parts, and the watriſh ſubſtance, only that which is contracted from aliment: For ſo long as the Grape was conjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Vine, there did flow there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto a watriſh humour by which it was nouriſhed, and after the Grape is ſeparated from the Vine, ſtill doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20529:17"/>that wateriſh humour, which as yet was not converted, nor aſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the ſubſtance of wine, neither can have any further converſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the wine is now no more <hi>anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> or able to produce it into act. But this is that humidity in wine which is ſpent and waſted in boyling or otherwiſe, and the other heate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth only which is innate, and fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the ſubſtance of wine; and hence it is that the boyling of wine makes it more ſweet, the other humidity being thus ſpent, it returnes to its true natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall moiſture; And this I hope will be a ſufficient ſatisfaction for the nature of wine in generall, from whence its familiarity with humane nature will appeare.</p>
            <p>Now we proceed to the ſpecificall difference of wine, and wine, and theſe differences conſiſt chiefly in name, for although ſome differ among us in name, yet there is no ſpecificall diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20529:17"/>but if you take them naturally there is in ſuch a ſpecificall difference, which addeth to the name, as colour taſtes and ſmell; The nature of them all corroborative, nutritive, mundifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cative, apperitive, and theſe are not only teſtified by the ancient learned Phiſitians, but alſo proved out of their owne exiſtence or prime animation, which hereafter ſhall bee demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated.</p>
            <p>To returne therefore to the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in name or names they are ſo va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and endleſſe, as that will reliſh more of curioſity then utility, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, many of them being more phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtically impoſed, out of the exube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſingularity in Merchants of all nations. But ſo many as Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, Phiſitians, or Poets have taken notice of, I ſhall briefly ſet downe, and ſo paſſe to the colours.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place let us take notice of the generall name <hi>Vinum,</hi> and ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20529:18"/>
               <hi>à vi,</hi> from the ſtrength of it, as <hi>Varro</hi> would have it, but I rather ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it <hi>vinum quaſi divinum,</hi> and ſo a ſpecies of the tree of life in Paradiſe. The Ancients they had many ſorts of wine differing in name, as <hi>Fortinum</hi> newly expreſt from the grape, <hi>Proto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum,</hi> ſuch as fell from the Vine before the grapes were trodden; others which take their names from the regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in which they grow: as <hi>Chium, Lesbium, Falernum, Caecubum, Surrenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, Calenum, Signinum, Tarraconenſe, Spoletinum, Ceretanum, Fundanum, Malvaticum;</hi> amongſt the French ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others: as <hi>vinum Belonenſe, Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onenſe, Monliſpedonenſe, Remenſe, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>degalenſe, Aurelianenſe, Andegavenſe,</hi> and theſe agree better with ſound bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies in preſerving their temper then with infirme conſtitutions. There are weake wines in France which agree better with feaveriſh diſpoſitions, then with cold phlegmatick tempers: as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20529:18"/>
               <hi>Pariſienſe, Limonicenſe, Forenſe, Allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brogenſe,</hi> with many other. But now you know their names, and partly to what temper they are proper let us take a taſte, and principally ſtrike theſe foure veſſels, <hi>(viz.) ſweet, acute, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtere, and milde,</hi> obſerving alſo foure colours in them, <hi>(viz.) white, ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous, yellow,</hi> and <hi>blacke,</hi> the firſt three commonly uſed and knowne to us by the names of White, Claret, and Sack, and theſe alſo admit of their differences: for there are ſeverall ſorts of Sack and Claret, ſo alſo are there of white wines, ſome ſweet, ſome au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtere, ſome thick, others lympid and cleere, and all theſe nouriſh much, but eſpecially the ſweet wine, with this caution, that the liver, ſpleene, and reines, bee void of obſtruction; For the ſweeteſt Wines, (though they nouriſh moſt) yet becauſe they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a body generally more craſſe: therefore they are ſaid to obſtruct
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20529:19"/>very much. Now having Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phically ſhewed their nature and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence ſpecifically, it remaines that I offer them medicinally to publike view.</p>
            <p>The qualities generally received a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Phiſitians are to nouriſh, <hi>Et ſuper omnia alimenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> if you will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the teſtimony of <hi>Galen;</hi> It doth alſo evacuate, corroborate, correct putrefaction, open obſtructions, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilarate the ſpirits: and what more is wanting or needfull for the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or reſtauration of life and health then theſe, except we ſhould preferre circumſtance before ſubſtance, nor can there be any thing more ſecurely practiſed, then that which is ſo fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to nature, and univerſall princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of mixt bodies, or humane tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers: or ſo undoubtedly knowne to us in our Region, in any of theſe reſpects incomparable either with vegetall or minerall. For though we be very cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20529:19"/>in our ſcrutation, wee ſhall find either a difference irreconciliable in their figure or quality, and for the laſt, if it bee argued home in moſt drugges, it will put us, or rather force us to our hidden quality, and if wee ſpeake of remote drugges which are tranſported from other Regions, then I dare bee bold to ſay wee know them not at all, or not in ſuch a degree of perfection as wee ought: conſidering the frequent uſe of them. However the uſe of them cannot but be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; for if we know them, either wee cannot have them, or elſe ſuch is their alteration and change in tranſportati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as muſt force us to fault the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents for their high commendation of them, we finding either no ſuch ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues as they affirme of them, or none ſo effectuall as they avouch.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe <hi>Chriſtophorus Barri</hi> a Ieſuite in his relation to the Pope, of <hi>Cochin-china,</hi> profeſſeth that the rhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barb
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20529:20"/>which hee brought with him from thence, was ſo changed in tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation from what it was, as that he did not know it to bee the ſame thing either by the vertue or colour of it. And <hi>Symphorianus</hi> a learned Phiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, hath adventured to challenge moſt of our pharmacall compoſitions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this very ground, and doth affirme the chiefe ingredients to be altogether unknowne or found in the ſhops of European Apothecaries: For better ſatisfaction take this expreſſion in his owne words; <hi>Sed quòd res quaſdam vel non afferri, vel non ſine macula, vel in totum ignorari puto: ea ſunt balſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Cardamomum, Myrrha, Nardus indica, Caſsia, Scordium, Cinnamomum, radix Pentaphylli, Calamus odoratus, Xylobalſamum;</hi> Now if no man hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto hath anſwered his challenge, which for my owne part I ſuppoſe unanſwerable. Then let us view our Pharmacopea, and judge what uſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20529:20"/>can be made of our greateſt compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. How uncertaine, how unſafe the practice of them which in a plaine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion is but <hi>pugnare contra hoſtem clauſis oculis.</hi> I could ſtart other doubts about many other things much in uſe amongſt us, as Unicornes horne, and Bezoard-ſtone, or ſuch like; but my intention is not to enter into controverſie; yet deſire either to be better informed, or elſe to informe others, for which cauſe I now fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this ſubject, ſo well knowne to all Nations, that there is ſuch a thing as Wine, and that this or that, is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out queſtion ſuch a kind of wine, and familiarly uſed in this or that place; And if I prove not the aforeſaid qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities to be in it, I neither looke to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie my ſelfe nor the reader. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that which was laſt in my intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall now bee firſt in execution; And though I make not an Index of Authors, yet now my arguments ſhall
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20529:21"/>be altogether a Teſtimonie not doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in our ſubſequent diſcourſe to cleere the point more artificially.</p>
            <p>The firſt then is, That wine nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth above all other aliment; they that have read <hi>Galen,</hi> know theſe are his words tranſlated. Indeed ſome nouriſh more, ſome leſſe, according to their ſpecificall quality, as <hi>Vina a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quea perexiguum alimentum corpori praebent, quae verò craſſa ſunt &amp; colore rubea plus alimenti habent quàm reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua vina, Gal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that it doth corroborate, <hi>Vinum confortat ſpiritum, &amp; ad ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum convertitur, &amp; fortificat virtutem, Avicenna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, that it doth evacuate, <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacraſſa dulcia<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> quod alvum deijciant nemini ferè ignotum eſt, ſicut muſtum, quod tametſi aegrè concoquatur craſſum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuccum, &amp; inflationes faciat, alvum ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men movet, Gal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, that it doth open obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20529:21"/>
               <hi>Vinum dulce vehementer aperit oppilationes pulmonis, Avicenna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, that it doth exhilarate the ſpirits, take ſacred Scripture; ſo that hitherto I have cleered, and plainly diſcovered theſe qualities in wine me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dically, and confirmed all by ancient claſſick authority. Yet if further ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction be expected, then looke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the qualities of Wine in groſſe, as they are obviouſly laid downe by moſt or all the chiefeſt Ancients. White wine may bee adhibited in all acute and hot diſtempers, <hi>ut voluit Hippo.</hi> Sweet wine in cold diſeaſes, becauſe it heateth the body more, yet <hi>cum calefactione temperata, Gal.</hi> No White wine is ſweet, and that which is pure and ſubtile moveth Urine very much, leaveth no impreſſion in the head, becauſe it doth not manifeſtly heate, it doth ſenſibly refrigerate, and is commanded to bee adminiſtred in <hi>febre continua, Gal.</hi> Wine in generall
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20529:22"/>taken moderately, doth purge choler by Vrine, exhilarate the mind, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh the ſenſes; Wine alſo that is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute may ſafely be given in Fevers, and White wine doth manifeſtly refrige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and cleanſe the lungs, ſweet Wines alſo may be taken in acute paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, as Pluriſies and infla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mations of lungs to provoke expectoration, when the matter is digeſted according to <hi>Oribaſius, Haliabbas, Conſtantius Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nachus.</hi> Wine alſo that is white, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, and thinne, is not turbulent to the ſtomack, but of eaſie digeſtion, ſoone penetrateth the veines, provoketh u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, and is profitable in Fevers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it doth not make hot the body, or diſturbe the mind, nor offend either braine or nerves. But if it bee mixt then it quencheth thirſt better, if you will credit <hi>Iſaac</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Salomon,</hi> an Arabian King.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, White wine is ſaid to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipid, dilute, coagulate with cold, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20529:22"/>in ſuch are more parts of water then of wine; yet under favour in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of its univerſall parts, there can be no ſuch coagulation, as is affirmed by <hi>Iohannes Portugalenſis,</hi> once a Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi> Theſe are the generall opinions of the Ancients; But reaſon ſtill urgeth to prove further the poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of theſe ſeeming contraries in one and the ſame nature, as to open and ſhut, or ſhut and open, to corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate and weaken, or to weaken and ſtrengthen, and that theſe contrary acts ſhould appeare together at the ſame time, in the ſame ſubject to whom it is applyed; As that wine (as you have heard) ſhould generally eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuate excrements of the body, or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly purge bilious matter by urine, and yet the ſame ſpecificall wine ſhall corroborate the whole and every part it worketh upon at the ſame time: But when I conſider or contemplate the ſuper-excellency of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20529:23"/>this plant in a naturall perfection and mixture tranſcending all other vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, as doth plainly appeare by the purity of its nature in it ſelfe, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity with all animals; then it doth not ſeeme ſo unreaſonable, to grant it in its temper a complicate mixture, or comprehenſive nature, and to comprehend the quality of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Plants inferiour to it ſelfe; and in its owne perfection to obtaine a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, though not ſo high as in the more proper ſubject. And thus is man the Epitome of the whole world. How ever wee know theſe aforeſaid qualities to bee in wine, and may bee with as little contradiction as in <hi>Guia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum</hi> which doth by conſtringing eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuate, and <hi>Rhubarb</hi> which doth bind by purging. But ſtill I ſpy more poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility then that, which is only extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted out of a Simile: and this is <hi>ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid Catholicum,</hi> or an incorruptible ſpirit in Wine more powerfull then in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20529:23"/>any other ſuch thing. And this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth freely contracting or dilating its ſelfe in its ſpheare, adde diſtance wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker or ſtronger according to the power of the forenamed agent, and diſpoſition of the Spheare wherein it moveth. It may alſo be ſaid to move thus from its materiall principles, as by vertue of its fluent and fixt heate, the one oleaginous continuating, bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and uniting the parts together, the other fluent attenuating the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and looſening the belly or the body univerſally. And thus it is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to effect theſe contrary actions out of its owne naturall mixture. And ſince it can doe thus, there is a great deale of reaſon why it ſhould be thus practiſed, for there is no other vegetal or minerall ſo ſafe, harmleſſe and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar in it ſelfe to humane conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as being naturally more pure, and better concocted then any other juyce, either of milke, egges, corne,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:20529:24"/>fruits, or the like: all of them more ſubject to putrefaction, &amp; more one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to nature in concoction, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their crudity, the moſt of them breeding little bloud, or vitious bloud, or no bloud at all; But wine, eſpecially Claret or red, is ſanguified before it be taken: Nay, the Ancients ſeeme to perſwade mee (when they call it the old mans milke, that it hath received a concoction more then bloud, as it is cited in <hi>Iecore.</hi> For milke is bloud dealbated or thrice concocted. This is the phiſick which doth not dull, but ſet a true edge upon nature, after operation leaveth no venemous contact. Sure I am this was ancient Phiſick, elſe what meant <hi>Avicenna, Rhaſis,</hi> and <hi>Averroes,</hi> to move the body twice every month with the ſame, as it is familiar to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo they uſed it as familiarly; As for my own experience, though I have not lived yet ſo long, as to love ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20529:24"/>yet have I ſeene ſuch powerfull effects, both on my ſelfe and others, as if I could render no other reaſon, they were enough to perſwade me of its excellencie, ſeeing extenuate wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered bodies, by it cauſed to be faire, freſh, plumpe, and fat, old and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme to be young and ſound, when as water or ſmall-beere-drinkers, looke like Apes rather then men.</p>
            <p>My eye now is converted to the vulgar, and I ſee their hearts dance <hi>ſyſtole</hi> and <hi>diaſtole,</hi> diſorderly without obſervation of true time, the heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too much dilated with this report of preſervation from death, ſickneſſe, and paine. For naturall death, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame old age, ſuffereth diſſolution without any paine, and all theſe to bee affected by ſo familiar a medicament as Wine, this ſurely verifieth the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>Every man now must bee a foole or a Phyſician.</hi> But bee not deceived, the application of this medicament, to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20529:25"/>every temper, age, diſtemper, with its circumſtances of Sex and Clime, will exerciſe the beſt Philoſopher rightly to diſpoſe and order, and if diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly applied, or ignorantly adviſed, the principles of Nature muſt ſuffer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, and in ſtead of being extended ſhall bee ſweetly ſhortned, how ſweet then muſt extenſion bee! Empericks here ſtand like <hi>Tantalus</hi> with apples at their mouth, but cannot be the better for them; They ſee this ſubject but can never reach it, their Logick from a particular to an univerſall is of no force here; nor in this courſe can any man have experience, but he that knoweth what he doth in every one of theſe reſpects following, which are not rightly to be apprehended by any Emperick <hi>quatenùs</hi> an Emperick. Yet before I fall upon the foreſaid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, give me leave ſince I ſee <hi>Plato</hi> to ſalute him: <hi>amicus Plato, magis ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca veritas.</hi> The prohibition he bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20529:25"/>concerneth Kings, Magiſtrates, Souldiers, Women and ſervants, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely forbidding Wine at any time, place, or to any of theſe perſons, and confineth them altogether to water; So that whether hee meant none but the Common-wealth of Schollers, ſhould enjoy this happineſſe makes no matter, for aſſuredly hee chiefly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended ſobriety; Yet reaſon is not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, nor is his politique rule or law ſo agreeable to reaſon, as to bee recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in any Republique (except Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonicall.) Firſt, becauſe it binds thoſe from the uſe of Wine which are moſt capable of it, in reſpect of judgement and reaſon, which Princes and Iudges have above other people, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore know how to uſe it rightly: and being continually in ſervices of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, care, and paine, exhauſting their ſpirits and courage, ſtand in need of ſuch a refreſhment as ſhall exhilarate the mind, and maintaine the principles
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20529:26"/>of nature. What panick feares doth Wine prevent in the Souldier ſubtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their drooping ſpirits, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were quenched with puddle wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and in time of famine how doth this cheriſh and defend their bodies againſt diſtempers, which by other ſtinking vnſavoury meat and drinke might be generated. As for ſervants, this is meat for their maſters, but Phyſick for them upon juſt occaſion. And ſo I paſſe to the tempers of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies in generall, and the Wines gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally agreeing with thoſe tempers, and then more directly to this or that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividuall.</p>
            <p>Temper it ſelfe being the reaſon of mixture, or the harmony and conſent of the prime qualities in elements, and by the exuperancy of each ſimple quality; theſe foure ſimple tempers are created; as hot when the heate ſurpaſſeth the cold, and yet of ſiccity and moiſture remaineth an equality,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20529:26"/>and ſo of the reſt, as cold, and dry, and moiſt. Beſides, there are foure conjugate tempers which proceed from the exuperancy of the two firſt qualities, as hot and moiſt, hot and dry, cold and moiſt, cold and dry, which are the foure compound tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers; their fixation conſiſting in that oleaginous humour which wee call <hi>innatum calidum:</hi> and this innate ſo praeſtantious, ſo neceſſary, as without it mixt bodyes cannot ſubſiſt; 'tis alſo fomented, and cheriſhed by influent heate, contracted in the heart, veines and arteries, as their proper channels conſiſting of ſpirituall bloud, lying hid in the heart as the middle of the body, which by ſympathie doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and maintaine innate heate, and doth abſolve and perfect the tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with all the functions of the body, even as the Sunne like a blazing Lampe inlighteneth the world, ſo doth the heart ejaculate the influent
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20529:27"/>ſpirit, into the univerſall body, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprinkling every part, conſerving life, and excitating to particular functions, ſo as in truth ſuch as is this fluent ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſuch is the innate or ſixt ſpirit in power, and accordingly all the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in a corporall Republique ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred, which by ſence and reaſon are plainly comprehended, ſo that the excellency of this fluent heate is not only admirable, but alſo of abſolute neceſſitie. And if ſuch a cauſe may be admitted, as we call <hi>cauſa ſine qua non,</hi> then this may be ſo accepted; for without this mutuall commerce of fluent and innate heate, all bodily acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are ſtayed and quiet. Theſe being then the prime exiſtence and ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence of humane nature, and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full agents both in conformation and nutrition, their Spheare of motion may be more or leſſe adaptated by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall meanes, either homogeneall, or heterogeneall. For tempers then in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20529:27"/>generall, there is no ſuch aliment, no ſuch medicament as Wine. For the ſmalleſt wine, is a truer <hi>pabulum</hi> to the fluent ſpirit then egges, or milke ſucked from any creature, they all laying ſome burthen upon Nature to concoct, and in concoction there muſt be ſome expence both of fluent and radicall heate, and by ſo much is mans life ſhortened. But Wine is ſo pure in its owne nature, that it recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth a ſudden mutation, and in this very alteration addeth light and heate to the fore-named principles; and it is as oyle to thoſe naturall lampes, therefore to bee preferred in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fernelius</hi> ſeemeth to favour my reaſon, where hee ſaith, that diſeaſes that are cold, admit of a ſafer reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy or cure then hot diſtempers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>contraria contrarijs curantur,</hi> and thus regularly applying to the cold affect; wee foment and maintaine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20529:28"/>heate. Contrarily in taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way praeternaturall heate in the other, naturall heate doth either ſuffer, or is extinguiſhed: but both in cold and hot affects; Wine rightly applyed, and upon true judication, is the excellent and inoffenſive remedie. That it is a remedy, and ſuch a remedy I ſhall thus indeavour to prove.</p>
            <p>If it were by the ancient Phiſitians given as a wholſome and ſafe remedy in Feavers, then is it a remedie in hot diſeaſes, but ſo it hath beene applyed by the Ancients, as is before ſhewed. Againe, if it hath beene alſo by the ſame authority affirmed and adhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in cold affects; Then 'tis a proved remedy in both. And if wee take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with us the ſpecificall difference of Wine, then we ſhall ſoone obſerve this remedy to bee regular according to the Rule of contrariety. For Wine as it is naturally apperient, it openeth obſtruction; and oppilation is the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20529:28"/>next cauſe of putrefaction, and putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of Feavers, ſo that opening being contrary to oppilation; Wine being opening is a true contrary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy <hi>per ſe</hi> in obſtruction, and <hi>per accidens</hi> in the putrid Feavers.</p>
            <p>Now let me deſcend to particular affects of each kind, hot and cold, and in either of theſe prove Wine to bee a ſpecificall remedy, agreed upon by counſels aſwell as the foreſaid Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, beginning with a Iew that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured with melancholy, his temper hot and dry, from a vitious praedomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over the bloud, his body leane, colour black, ill diſpoſed to ſleepe, prompt to all actions, prone to anger, of an excellent wit and diſcourſe, but at this time mute, and hath beene ſo for Six dayes, his temper thus agreed upon with his diſtemper in a counſell of Doctors, they come now to ſix upon two wayes of cure, the one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of humectation, the other ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:20529:29"/>obſtruction, and in reſpect of both, Wine is concluded a proper re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy.</p>
            <p>Another great conſultation was had about one of the Chanons of <hi>Rome</hi> labouring with a Feaver, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no Wine might be preſcribed. About this point was much contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, and at laſt concluded and adhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited the remedie; For in all this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult I read of no other medicament.</p>
            <p>In the next place I preſent a young Gentle-woman epilepticall, or labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with the falling ſickneſſe, her tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per hot and moiſt, and ſo concluded in counſell; for they found her body fat and fleſhie: In this caſe they determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Wine to be moſt convenient for the attenuation of humours, and to be adminiſtred as a ſpecificall remedy; This alſo was agreed upon in a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Feaver for a young Spaniard: in a great diſtillation <hi>pro Epiſcopo Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſi:</hi> in various affects and diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers:
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20529:29"/>
               <hi>pro Aloyſio Fos Careno,</hi> in <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigine,</hi> proceeding from a cold and moiſt diſtemper of the braine: <hi>pro Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve Lucenſi</hi> againſt all affects of the kidnies and bladder, <hi>pro Magnifico Contareno,</hi> with many others which were eaſie to produce, were it not prolix.</p>
            <p>Enough being ſpoken to prove Wine in all tempers to bee proper ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in all diſtempers as proper medicament, concluded by Fathers, and Councels in medicine: thus farre have I urged Wine in its owne ſimple nature, not but that I take notice of medicate Wines, and their excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies in diſtempers above ſimple wine; So I paſſe to every age and ſexe, and ſhew how it is to bee uſed as aliment, and at what times.</p>
            <p>Humane bodies are not only ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious daily to affects of ayre, dyet, exerciſe, paſſions of the mind, &amp;c. but alſo from our implanted and internall
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20529:30"/>heate, which by little and little doth dry up and demoliſh our originall humidity, which ariſeth out of it ſelfe, and doth ſo depopulate and waſte it, as that it doth bring upon it many mutations, which are conſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed with certaine periods and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions of ages. For every Animall newly ſprung <hi>ex ſemine &amp; ſanguine,</hi> as it were compounded of its prime humidity, is moſt humid, in whom all parts aſwell bones and cartilages, as fleſh, are ſoft, tender, and fluxible, which by progreſſion in age doth ſtiffen, dry, wither, and conſume. In like manner are the mutations and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſitudes, of temperaments, faculties, humours, diſtempers and manners. Therefore age is but a courſe and ſpace, in which the conſtitution of the body by it ſelfe is perſpicuouſly altered and changed.</p>
            <p>Six notable differences of ages with their temperaments are to bee obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20529:30"/>The firſt is Child-age, which from the birth is extended to the foureteenth or fifteenth yeare, and this hot and moiſt, and is more hot then ripe and juvenall age, by reaſon of fixt, not fluent heate; for by how much neerer it is to its originall, by ſo much the more doth it participate of innate heate. Contrarily by how much it doth recede from its firſt Principles, by ſo much is this innate heate exhauſted. And this firſt age, one of the Ancients divideth into foure orders <hi>(viz.)</hi> Infancy, Dentity, and another betweene this and ripe age, and then puberity it ſelfe, which alſo comes in fitly and opportunely to bee diſcourſed, becauſe 'tis the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond age in the order of Nature. This age of puberity beginneth at the Fifteenth yeare, and is extended to the Eighteenth, and is leſſe moiſt and more hot. The third age is adoleſcency, beginneth at the Eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20529:31"/>yeare, and is extended to Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty five, and of a middle temper. The fourth age is juvenile or flouriſhing yong age, which beginneth at the Five and twentieth yeare, and extends to Thirty five, and in compariſon with the next foregoing age, is of a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per hot and dry. The fift age is vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rile or manly, and the conſtant me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia, betweene flouriſhing young age and old age; Yet doth it not ſo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate of either, as that it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperate or infected thereby: it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth at Thirty five, and is exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded-to Fourty nine. The ſixt and laſt is Old age, which with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſtion of naturall heate, becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth cold and dry in temper, but excrementitiouſly moiſt, by reaſon of languiſhing heate. This laſt age alſo as the firſt doth admit of divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion into theſe three parts. The firſt is freſh old age, beginning at Fifty, and extendeth to Sixtie, and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20529:31"/>all this time may doe the Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique good ſervice, and execute offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as other men. The ſecond age is a <hi>media</hi> or middle old age, beginning at Sixtie, and extending to Seventie, and in this Claſſis, by reaſon of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall imbecillity, they cannot deſerve of the Common-wealth. The laſt is decrepid age, and this concludeth our life, and being in this life, it beginneth at Seventie, and is extended ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Eightie; And further, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the purity of naturall Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. Theſe are the periods and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences exactly of mans age; The firſt ingreſſe hot and moiſt, the laſt egreſſe cold and dry, the middle temperate, ſight and touch being ſenſible wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of this truth.</p>
            <p>Holy <hi>Iob</hi> teſtifieth with mee, that man ſpringeth up like a flower, and continueth not long in one ſtate. Thus having circled out mans life <hi>à puncto ad punctum,</hi> it will appeare
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20529:32"/>very probable, that mans life may by art be preſerved free from any diſeaſe, ariſing out of the mixture of naturall principles, from the infant age to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepid old age, except the Principles be caſt impure, from whence procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth weaker tempers, and many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempers which wee call hereditary di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes. And theſe alſo by art, and the artificial uſe and application of Wine, may be much altered, and life beyond all expectation prolonged. For the nature of Wine is ſo agreeable, and familiar with the naturall principles, of man, as if by the Phiſitian it be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly applyed, it ſhall ſo ſtrengthen the weakeſt temper, as ſhall make it ſubſiſt againſt a forcible diſtemper conveyed in <hi>materia ſpermatica.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The beſt opportunity of performing or acting this duty is <hi>ab incunabulis,</hi> to take the child from the mothers breſt, and from temper to temper to proceed, otherwiſe the temper uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20529:32"/>may be ſpoyled before, or ſo injured by unskilfull application of medicaments, as may cauſe to faile in the underſtanding. Yet much time may be gained in any ſuch caſe, and that which is counted the ſhame of Phiſitians, and puts them ſo often to their wits ends <hi>(viz.)</hi> a Conſumption hereditary or accidentall, and univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of the whole body, is no way to be cured better than by the right uſe of this plant. All Phiſitians in this caſe have hitherto flone to milke of Aſſes, and the like; But what is milke, comparatively with this juyce, which indeed is fit for Princes to receive, and Phiſitians duly to ſtudy upon, that they may learnedly and rightly apply it? For as Kings are the life and ſoule of the Republique and State, ſo for this cauſe, great care and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ought to be urged for their ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the extenſion of their lives to extreame age healthfully; which in
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:20529:33"/>many hath beene ſhortened by Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landiſh devices, and kickchawes. But if the learnedeſt Phiſitians ſhall throughly contemplate this ſubject, they ſhall ſoone ſee where the extenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Kings lives is involved; <hi>Experto crede Roberto.</hi> I ſpeake not phantaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, or from any palate-pleaſure. For my owne ſickly temper durſt not within theſe few yeares, ſo much as taſte Wine, til time and ſtudy enabled my judgement better, and now I take it daily, and (by the concurring bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of the Almighty) and not thinne and extenuate, as formerly I have beene, but ſound and ſtrong as any of my yeares that hath had ſo many violent ſickneſſes. I could alſo ſpeake of ſtrange effects I have wrought in others, but leſt I ſhould be challenged for oſtentation I will forbeare, it being alſo a thing ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what unjuſt, to publiſh perſons and their imperfections to the world,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20529:33"/>which were privately committed to my care. Nor is teſtimony in this caſe needfull, ſince I have proved the probability of effecting theſe or ſuch like, by reaſon, and argued the nature and mixture of this ſubject philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phically, and upon this ground I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire rather to bee credited, then upon any other. And ſo I will returne from my digreſſion, and take up my ſubject againe, and ſee if I can fit it now to all ages.</p>
            <p>The Infant age is the firſt and moſt difficult (as ſome thinke) to reconcile, becauſe <hi>Galen</hi> ſaith, <hi>vinum Infanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſit nocivum,</hi> by reaſon of their temper, which is hot and moiſt; And ſo they underſtand <hi>Galen</hi> to ſpeake of the qualitie, but hee was not ſo weake a Philoſopher or Logician, as not to underſtand that mixt bodies are main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, preſerved, and nouriſhed by their Simile. Nor did hee ever argue againſt <hi>ijs nutrimur quibus conſtamus,</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:20529:34"/>which is to bee underſtood of mixt qualities rightly applyed, that ſuch are moſt apt and diſpoſed in their owne nature to aſſimilate with their like, as is this mixture in Wine to our materiall Principles of nature; So that <hi>Galen</hi> cannot bee underſtood to ſpeake of the quality, but rather the quantitie exceeding juſt proportion, with the manner of application, as if by the exceſſive quantity, you will adde ſo much oyle to the Lampe as ſhall extinguiſh it, or at ſuch times when it ſhall diſturbe it, by moving of ſome other heterogeneall, with time of it ſelfe, with the helpe or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret and inſenſible motion of Nature will conſume. But had the mixture in it ſelfe beene hurtfull, there would appeare but little reaſon in <hi>Hippocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> which dyeteth children which are hereditarily ſubject to the ſtone, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the bladder or reines, with white Wine rather then with milke.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:20529:34"/>Now hee was not ignorant of diſeaſes hereditarie, that they are conveyed to the children in the Principles of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: and that Wine in it ſelfe was moſt agreeable to maintaine their conſtitutions, without any alteration of it to move affectedly; my ſelfe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo have adviſed it, and not only in the ſame caſe, but alſo in Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and many other affects with ſingular ſucceſſe: And (in truth) if Wine hurt any temper, the diſcretion of the Agent is to bee queſtioned, not well obſerving or knowing the true ſpecificall differences each way.</p>
            <p>By theſe expreſſions I hope, thoſe that underſtand beleeve alſo, that the firſt is ſet at libertie to make uſe of Wine; now I muſt preſent a health to the next, which wee called Pubertie, this temper is more hot, and leſſe moiſt then the former. So that by way of contemperation of the heate, and humectation of the moiſt, the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:20529:35"/>ſame Wine is ſtill uſefull and moſt proper. But when, and how long, and how much, and how fitted is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowne to the Phiſitian, and hee guided by his judications.</p>
            <p>Adoleſcency, which is the <hi>media,</hi> or of a middle temper, neither hot nor cold, may not feare either White, Claret, or Rheniſh, in their order, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the ſeaſons; with the inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of celeſtiall orbes, and the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iuventus,</hi> being more hot and dry, muſt alſo apply himſelfe to theſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named Wines, ſomewhat more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, which is eaſily effected by water.</p>
            <p>Virile age holds out a cup of more rich Claret from 35 to 49. and goeth out with a draught of the ſmalleſt Sacke. Which <hi>Senectus</hi> makes ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger by addition of Aligants, and the richeſt Sacks and Muſcadine, and continueth them unto the laſt period of life.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:20529:35"/>
            <p>Thus have I now applied it gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to every age, and briefly cleered my propoſition. As for the Sex, male or female; betweene theſe I ſhall make no difference of temper. Nor doe I give eare to ſome, that make foule ſtirre <hi>de Lana Caprina,</hi> or to prove divers temperaments of Sexes, and that the procreation of women is more in the left then in the right ſide; <hi>Ergo,</hi> they muſt bee more cold, and more weake; But whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they fancy this is only to bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, without any further diſpute; That temperaments are not conflate, out of heate more obtuſe, or vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but depend on the perfuſion and conſent of the foure Elements. Therefore having diſtinctly diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of temperaments, I have alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded Sexes; As for the manner of uſing this ſubject. Thus it is as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p>Hitherto I have taught the nature
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:20529:36"/>and uſe of Wine, both Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, and medically, and how fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar a nutriment it is to man, and ſtill ſay it muſt bee ſo, both in reſpect of its ſubſtance and forme, elſe I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> his <hi>alimentum ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile</hi> and <hi>diſsimile;</hi> For although all aliment of what ſubſtance ſoever muſt receive forme of heate before it bee converted into bloud, by which it doth nouriſh both fluent and fixt heate in us. Yet ſuch nor ſo apt is any ſubſtance for forme to ſanguifie or nouriſh as Wine; and if it be poſſible, it will augment innate heate and moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture; For 'tis oyle not water that aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the flame, a proportion obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, elſe it puts it out: ſo that it is the true Nectar, by the uſe whereof Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of life are augmented, naturall humours multiplied, ſpirits refreſhed, ſtrength reſtored, care expelled, and bodies in youthfulneſſe conſerved. To conclude, 'tis all in all to a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:20529:36"/>body. For although in generall, aliment is ſaid to bee liquid, airie, and ſolid, yet 'tis humidity that nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. For medicament alſo I have proved it proper; The <hi>Arabian</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians are of opinion, that to take this liquor once every moneth, in ſuch a quantitie as ſhall be approved by the learned Phiſicians is wholſome Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, it doth much recreate the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal faculties, reconcile ſleep, provoke urine, and ſweat, diſſolve ſuperfluities, and they affirme it to cure the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane with other diſeaſes, circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces conducing to the profitable uſe of it after this manner, which circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances I obſcure, becauſe I am deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to entertaine time with ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, only Cuſtome is to be mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as ſomewhat ſubſtantiall, for it over-ruleth the reſt; and the time ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally moſt fit to receive Wine is with meate, and then ſuch Wine as beſt fitteth the temper of the Indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duall;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:20529:37"/>But thoſe that meane to uſe this ſubject rightly muſt not be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their Phiſitian, or out of their view, for let their temper or diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per bee what it will, ſo it be not ſome fatall ſtroke, or wound; by the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Phiſitian and his skill, they may ſinſibly perceive the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longation of their life, and by this meanes, which is ſo pleaſant to uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall Nature. The Chymiſt his beſt Rhetorick is exerciſed about the pleaſantneſſe of his extract, ſmalneſſe of quantitie. But here I preſent a taſte for pleaſure, beyond all mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls forſafetie, 'tis incomparable ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with them or Vegetals. Exceſſe in this may be more eaſily repaired; nor is the offence in nature of ſo great moment. Now becauſe there will be ſome difficultie in getting true natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Wine without ſophiſtication, therefore I ſhould thinke it fit (were it ſo pleaſing to Authority whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:20529:37"/>I humbly ſubmit) that as it hath beene heretofore with us, and is ſtill in other Countryes, Apothecaries might have libertie to ſell it, and ſo by the direction of the Phiſitian, to make many medicate Wines, fitted and in readineſſe upon all occaſions. But that I may draw to a concluſion, I will briefly lay downe (or rather take up) two maine objections, one moved by <hi>Galen,</hi> the other from the ſacred Scripture, apprehended erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niouſly: both indeed at the firſt view or blaſt will ſeeme to ſhake both my foundation and edifice alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Galen</hi> after all his ratiocination, is raiſed out of his Urne, and preſents to me in his Commentary upon the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoriſmes theſe words; Wine debili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tateth as <hi>Venus:</hi> and <hi>Frambeſarius</hi> makes bold with his doctrine, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livereth it for a truth, and in theſe words, <hi>Vinum Venuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nocent eodem modo.</hi> The objection I confeſſe is <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtar
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:20529:38"/>omnium,</hi> and very materiall, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee be taken to ſpeake of the uſe or exceſſe of Wine. In the firſt ſence it doth oppoſe all that I have former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taught and proved, in the laſt a fit oppoſition to <hi>Avicenna, Rhaſis,</hi> and <hi>Averrohes,</hi> they adviſing wine once a moneth, <hi>uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad obrietatem.</hi> Now if <hi>Galen</hi> bee not underſtood to ſpeake of exceſſe, then (as I have ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) neither Wine nor Venery, can hurt, debilitate, and weaken the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, for both rightly uſed are profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the one to preſerve the individual, the other to propagate the ſpecies, and <hi>venus</hi> as well as <hi>vinum,</hi> both exhila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the minde, cheare the ſpirits, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frigerate the body, and cauſe ſleepe. So that at the firſt view, <hi>Galen</hi> doth ſeeme to ſpeake of exceſſe only, or principally. But that I may reconcile him with the <hi>Arabian</hi> Phiſitians my part is now to explicate, and render him in his owne proper ſence and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:20529:38"/>meaning. This exception is not ſo much, or principally againſt the quantity, as the qualitie and miſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, both in reſpect of time and temper. As when the quality of wine exceedeth in ſtrength the temper of the body, to which it is given, and at a time unſeaſonable, as upon a faſting ſtomacke, and then to exerciſe the act of Venery, intemperatly upon it: and in this ſence is <hi>Galen</hi> to bee conceived chiefly. But I apprehend <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Ambroſius</hi> in another ſence, meerely diſtaſting the <hi>nimium</hi> ebriety, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxication in a voluptuous way: and (to ſpeake truth) after ſuch manner abuſed, 'tis poyſon both to mind and body, inflameth the bloud, debilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the nerves, vexeth the head, and to bee ſhort is worſe then any poyſon. For this cauſe <hi>Moſes</hi> not only calleth it <hi>Venenum,</hi> but the poyſon of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons which admitteth of no cure. Therefore Wine in this manner taken,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:20529:39"/>and according to this ſence is more deteſtable, for the ſtrongeſt poyſon of Animalls or minerals can but vulne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the fleſh, but wine is powerfull to wound the ſoule; Yet ſuch is my candid cenſure of thoſe Arabian Princes in Medicine, that they never uſed it after this manner themſelves, or adviſed it in a voluptuous way to others (I meane to ebriety) but as a medicament rightly and properly ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated; Thus they made uſe of wine rather then any other medicament, becauſe of its familiarity with the Principles of humane Nature. Well knowing that ebriety, (as it is ſimply into xication) may be effected by other medicaments aſwell as wine, and if not wine, then wee are inforced to uſe the other for ſopori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficks, and the like. So that by this time I hope the doubt is cleere, the ancient Phiſitians reconciled, and my ſelfe moving towards the next obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:20529:39"/>grounded upon Scripture.</p>
            <p>There are a ſect in the world, and in this Region, that ſtiffely defend the fatality of mans life; and that no man can bee preſerved, prolonged, or reſtored. That diſeaſes of every kind are, or elſe to bee inflicted, by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expugnable neceſſity determined of God, and immutably fixed; And theſe <hi>Ignaroes</hi> have baſe and meane thoughts of thoſe which defend the contrary, ſuppoſing it to bee a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous curioſity to avoid contagion, to ſeeke remedies for diſeaſes, or to arme themſelves againſt their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, becauſe God foreſeeth death of this kind or the like; And the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty foreſeeing death of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and at this time, and to this or that individuall; <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is not to bee avoided, though the Lord ſhall ſay every mans perdition is of himſelfe. Dangerous and impious muſt this opinion needs bee, for if it be granted,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:20529:40"/>what needs the Church or any private perſon, put up any prayer to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, for the reſtauration of life and health, and preſervation out of danger? and to what end or purpoſe was the gift of healing diſpenced to the Phiſician, if death and diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of every kind bee predeſtinated, ſo as by no meanes it can bee ſhunned or prevented? Nay, to what end ſhould wee pray for our daily bread or health, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> That we may therfore expurge this pernicious and intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable miſtake concerning the divine providence of God, ſome things about his celeſtiall adminiſtration of univerſalls are more highly to bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into conſideration, and repeated: by which the dignity and eximious utilitie of medicine may bee fully ſhewed. That therfore the viciſſitudes of humane actions and things hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen not by chance or fortune, but by the ordination of the Almighty,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:20529:40"/>ought to bee embraced by all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian pious people, and that God is the omnipotent and eternall builder of the Univerſe, and framed it of nothing, as is proved by divine teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie. This building being thus po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfully framed, is alſo by the ſame efficacie conſerved, who hath alſo conſtituted to every particular crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thing by its ſelfe, a beginning and an end of ſubſiſting and moving, and doth take notice not only of princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall, but alſo of ſubſequent cauſes of things, as if the Lord did governe, moderate, diſpoſe and order them, according to his free will, and yet all this government is void of fatall vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and moſt commonly commeth to paſſe mediatly, and by deputed cauſes, which the vulgar call ſecond cauſes; which the divine Majeſtie doth uſe as the inſtruments of his will, while hee doth ſo manage all things which he hath created, as alſo him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:20529:41"/>may ſuffer them to exerciſe their proper motions; for the will of man by divine ordination is the beginning of humane actions, freely chooſing what ſeemeth beſt to its ſelfe, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in externalls. And according to <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> the nature of motion is the cauſe of this or that thing in which it is primarily <hi>&amp; per ſe.</hi> As for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in the Sunne, perpetuall rotation, in weights of their inclination to Center. Yea, the cauſes ſo anſwer the effects, as if the effects bee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, the cauſes are alſo neceſſary, and of contingents, the cauſes are alſo contingents; nor doth the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, which is certaine and cannot bee deceived take away the contingency of naturall events. But the future effect is diſpoſed, as it were by a divine providence, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily or contingently. Nor is it ſo that the Creatour is bound to the neceſſitie, but moderateth all things
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:20529:41"/>freely according to his free-will and pleaſure. As did plainely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, when hee cauſed the Sunne to ſtand ſtill a whole day. And when hee cauſed the Sea to divide it ſelfe and ſtand like firme walls about the Iſraelites; As alſo in the caſe of <hi>Daniel.</hi> The three chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in the fiery furnace. And <hi>Duffus Milcolumbus</hi> King of <hi>Scots,</hi> who being cruelly murthered, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 961. neither Sunne or Moone was ſeene for the ſpace of ſixe moneths after. And although hee can thus diſpoſe of cauſes, and life and death abſolutely at his own pleaſure, yet it behoveth us right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to take that conſtitution of tearme of life not abſolutely for a fatall determination; but for a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ordination of ſervient cauſes, by their naturall power of ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or corrupting life. For ſince
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:20529:42"/>life (as the Philoſopher ſpeaketh) is nothing but a duration of heate conjunct with moiſture, and dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of vitall heate, and extinction of the ſame, are naturall effects, depending in like manner upon na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall cauſes; which without doubt for the various internall diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of naturall heate and moiſture, as alſo externall cauſes, not only the quality, but alſo the quantity of life it ſelfe may bee varied. For it doth attaine the internall condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of lively Principles, ſo long as the heate and moiſture are ſo uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Animals, as one is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by the other, and ſo long they live, but either of theſe ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated each from other periſh. And in whomſoever innate is more vegetious and ſtrong, and radicall moiſture more pure in ſubſtance, copious in quantitie, and alſo tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:20529:42"/>in them life is more long. Thence it commeth to paſſe, that our ancient Fathers by reaſon of puritie in the internall cauſes of life, have exceeded the age of nine hundred yeares; Succeeding ages departing from that puritie of Principles, by little and little are come downe to ſhorter ages; And in theſe our ages, the Counteſſe of <hi>Deſmond,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Parre,</hi> are extraordinary examples. For or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary old age is Threeſcore and tenne, if more it muſt bee by the extraordinary power and purity of the radicall Principles; For radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call heate is the principall Agent of generation, in the liquid ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of ſeed and bloud in the firſt conception, ſoone after renders it more dry, and exhibits the rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of every member, and by drying ſtill more, doth publiſh the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:20529:43"/>exact ſpecies; Then it doth aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment after it is come into the world, and bringeth it to perfection. Hence by the continuate efficiency of the ſameheate, all the parts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exiccated above meaſure are leſſe able to adminiſtrate their offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whence followeth a neceſſitie of decay, and extinction at laſt of naturall heate, and this is a naturall death, according to <hi>Galen.</hi> Which by decrepid old age, by ſiccity and defect of nouriſhment, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſenſe of paine according to nature is extinct. And is unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and violent, when by any other internall or externall cauſe or injurie, it is put out before decrepid age; For ſo with care and skill it may bee prolonged. For as I have plainly argued, and yet not ſwarving from true naturall Philoſophy, by this right it doth
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:20529:43"/>appeare poſſible, to maintaine the Unitie of heate and moiſture till they ſpend themſelves in their owne naturall motion, and is to cut off their being by unskilfull courſes either in dyet or medicine.</p>
            <p>And if a Simile will bee accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, I ſuppoſe <hi>Hippocrates</hi> to bee very happy in his, when hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth the life of man to a candle in a Lanthorne, or ſet up in ſome other place, where neither wind or raine, or other tempeſt can ſeize upon it; In ſuch a place the candle will bee longer burning out, then when it is expoſed to common in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries of winde and weather, by which it is either ſuddenly blowne out, before the oyle or tallow bee ſpent, or elſe blazeth out in a ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter time. And theſe injuries are to the bodyes of men plagues, wounds, and all manner of diſeaſes,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:20529:44"/>compelling nature violently, to yeeld its naturall being; which otherwiſe might and would be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther extended.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe according to the truth of that, <hi>Contra vim mortis, non eſt medicamen in hortis;</hi> That naturall death cannot bee avoyded, becauſe the heart cannot bee made moiſter, when as by age it is exiccated; Yet I doe not thinke it wiſe or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, in a negligent way to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray our lives to death before the time, as ſome doe in a phantaſticall way, others in a deſperate, but all like fooles goe to the ſlaughter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, when as they runne upon ſuch dangers, <hi>inconſulto medico vel amico.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this time I hope the fatality of mans life will not bee queſtioned much, nor the poſſibility of exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it to extreame old age; and by
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:20529:44"/>no meanes ſo familiar and ſafe as Wine. Now if I ſhould proceed further to every circumſtance con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducible to the practicall part, it would bee a worke of long time, which I cannot well ſpare, and of exact judgement, wherein I could bee content to receive directions from others more able and learned then my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>That which I have done is ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to ſatisfie the world in the thing it ſelfe, which hath beene in allages queſtioned, both in reſpect of mans life, that it is not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended; As alſo in reſpect of Wines, that they are not ſo proper to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it. Now if you looke backe upon the Principles of mans life, and the Principles of wine, none will, I hope, condemne my Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, though ſome may differ in opinion, and many ſuch there will
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:20529:45"/>be, which in ſuch infinitie aſwell of judgements as of faces, cannot bee helped nor avoyded. Therefore it is not in me to ſatisfie every fancy, nor doe I deſire to bee underſtood of the Vulgar; But rather that wiſdome ſhould bee juſtified of her Children, and to ſuch are theſe my indeavours offered a ſacrifice, after the manner of thoſe devout Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> which by reaſon of ſudden inundation of waters were diſappointed of their yearely oblation, which they uſed to offer up to <hi>Iupiter,</hi> yet rather then they would bee wanting therein, they religiouſly concluded in ſtead of a Ram to offer a Limon, which <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> accepted in that caſe of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie.</p>
            <p>So my ſelfe having lately waded thorow Fountaines, Moores, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Pooles, Rivers, Wells, and the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:20529:45"/>Sea, it is impoſſible my braine ſhould bee free of Inundation, and conſequently my Wine pure with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mixture of water and much weakneſſe; Yet if my devotion may bee well pleaſing to <hi>Iupiter,</hi> let it be bleſſed to the world. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I have (like <hi>Hercules</hi> his dogge) but only beſmeared my lippes, with this Crimſon juyce, other <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> braines may vent it in a plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull manner, by which every ſenſe ſhall bee refreſhed, every ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity filled, and every underſtanding tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delighted.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:20529:46"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20529:46"/>
            <p>PVlchrum tuum, vir clariſsime, ac doctum de vine tractatum non oſcitanter perlegi, ac tibi remitto. Ab iſto ſubjecto Noacho ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomen obtigiſsê exiſtimo; Quum isto fuerit gentilium Ianus bifrons nullus dubito. Nota illi fuere, &amp; quae ante diluvium geſta, &amp; quae aliquot anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum centurijs poſt illud accidêre. Ille à liberaliore vini potu pudenda detexit; tu ab ingenio vini arcana in publicum bonum revelas. Si quis ſitqui ex aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dua Authorum lectione qui tibi viam praeruêre, exiſtimet ſe quae ad hanc materiam pertinent abundè percepiſſe nae ego illum exiſtimo latè falli. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniet in tuo opuſculo non pauca ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nus non obſervata, quibus inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus poſsit, &amp; quae in rem ſuam ſunt pervidere, &amp; aliorum ſanitati conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere.
<pb facs="tcp:20529:47"/>Quamobrem fra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>lign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> voris dente perge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> iui glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am aternitati conſecrare.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Scribebam Londini <date>
                     <hi>7</hi> Calend. Mart. anni. ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exhibito incarne Meſsiâ ſupra mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſimum ſexcenteſimum trigeſimi ſexti.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Tui ſi quis alius ſtudioſus, <hi>Alexander Reidus.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:20529:47"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Wykes R.P. Epiſc. Lond. Cap. domeſt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
